So today I'm going to be
talking about some recent work
that we've been
doing at DeepMind,
developing this line
of architectures
that we're calling perceivers.
And I'll be motivating this in
terms of a goal that we have,
which is to develop a general
purpose architectures.
And so just right
off the bat, I want
to motivate why we care about
general purpose architectures.
And so the first--
both of the reasons
are fairly pragmatic.
But basically the
idea is if we're
thinking about all of the
data that we could possibly
imagine collecting in
the world, a lot of it
is basically involved
in what we think
of as sort of traditional
sense modalities.
And these things range from
touch, and proprioception,
to echolocation, to
the kind of perception
you need to ingest texts--
however you want
to format that--
just to more exotic things
like event-based cameras,
touching with your senses--
things like smell and depth--
and all the way up to the
kinds of sense modalities
that we really think
about when we're thinking
about scientific perception.
And so basically if we think
about the full set of data
and what it would
take to actually model
each of these
different modalities,
it basically looks
effectively intractable to try
to the engineer inductive
biases that will work
for every single one of these.
So we don't want to
engineer them one by one.
This is an approach
that's worked.
And in some ways it's maybe
a reasonable description
of how we think about
developing new architectures
for different problems.
But it's just not
going to scale.
We can't afford as a
community to hand design
inductive biases that
will work for each
and every one of these.
And so rather than
doing that, we
want to sort of
build architectures
that at least a first pass will
allow us to handle everything.
There's another
practical argument
for why we should work on
general purpose architectures.
And that's because it will
allow us to build simpler
and more unified systems.
So if you look at
how, in particular,
complex multimodal data
streams are typically
approached in the sensory
computer vision or pattern
recognition literatures.
Effectively, the
typical way this is done
is by using inductive
biases that we now
hold for the
individual modalities,
and then engineer
ways of combining
those different subsystems.
So this can mean building
specific heads, specific input
modules for each
of these things,
and then trying out the
various different ways
of combining them.
So this can work,
but it gives us
systems that in principle
really will only work on one
or a small number of domains.
And it gives us systems that
are very hard to maintain,
tend to be fragile,
tend to depend
on specific processing
assumptions about the input
modalities.
So rather than do
that, we sort of
want to move in a
direction of having
unified black-box architectures
that kind of just work.
And the idea here is that
if we can get to that point,
we can abstract the architecture
construction process
and really focus on other
more high-level problems.
So this is sort
of the motivation
for this line of work.
And the way that we're
going to be doing this
is of course by working on
the most general purpose
architecture that
we have so far,
which is basically
a transformer.
And you'll all be very familiar
with the basic building
blocks of a transformer.
But just at a very
high level, we
can think about
what they do right,
which is they use a general
purpose inductive bias.
So they're non-local,
which means
they're not making domain
specific assumptions
about which point should
be compared to each other,
rather they tend to be global in
terms of the attentional focus
that they have.
They use a position as a feature
rather than a hard constraint
of the architecture.
And this is in contrast to
sort of NLP-based architectures
or ConvNets in the way
that they typically work,
which used position as an
architectural component
to constrain how
compute is happening.
And then of course
finally, there's
extensive weight sharing in the
way that that they're designed.
And because they
focus on Matmuls,
they tend to be TPU
and GPU friendly.
So these are all very
nice things about the way
transformers work.
Of course on the
other hand, they
have very poor compute
memory scaling.
And there are two
components to this.
So attention itself
scales quadratically.
So there's this O of
M squared L complexity
at the heart of transformers,
and I like writing it this way,
because it really emphasizes
that this is a property of--
basically as you make
your models bigger,
either at the input size
or as you make them deeper,
this problem is just
going to get worse.
And because you have this
scaling in depth as well,
there's another sort
of practical thing
that happens here because
the amount of compute
that we're doing is
proportional to the input size.
So there's no
bottleneck in the way
that standard transformers work.
Even the linear scaling
becomes a problem.
And so in practice for very,
very large transformers,
this can often be the
bottleneck that really matters.
But they're both at play here.
And so we really want to sort
of tamp down both of these.
And so the sort of
perspective here
is that to have really
general purpose architectures,
we can't have ones that are
just in principle general.
We have to have ones
that you can actually
use on the scales and the kinds
of data that we care about.
And so just to--
this will all be old
hat for all of you,
but just the way that
standard QKV attention
works is basically like this.
So it's all about
matrix multiplications.
So we have some input.
We compute the query
keys and values
by having a 1d convolution,
a 1 by 1 convolution
that we run over the input.
We then compute the
attention scores.
This is a matrix multiply
that has the following,
these sorts of shapes.
We then use the
output here to compute
the weights to compute the
actual output of the attention
module itself.
And then finally, we run this
through an additional MLP,
which is applied convolutionally
to get the outputs.
So this is the starting point
of what we're working on here.
And let me just
briefly just reiterate
why we would want the
sort of advantages
that we have with these sort
of standard transformers.
So non-locality is one of the
two inductive bias principles
that we have here.
It's useful, I think,
to contrast this
to way that the
effective locality
that you get in convnets and
what this actually means.
So if we look at basically as a
function of depth, which inputs
can see which other
ones, which means
like how easily it is to express
a function of two input points.
Let's say we look at these
this yellow and purple point
here at the input.
Now I set them sort of
as far apart as possible.
But we might ask how deep
would the effect of computation
have to be before you
actually process these two?
And if you look at a 3 by 3
convolution, you're talking--
you're having to look
basically until the very end
of the network until
you're processing
these things together.
And what this means
is that the functions
that you can express
that actually
look at both of these points
end up being quite shallow,
because they have
to be built on top
of this very, very deep
stack that just gives you
the locality.
And so in point of
fact, if you look at,
for example, the
way ResNets work,
so you have an initial block
which has a 7 by 7 convolution.
And then afterwards it's 3
by 3 columns all the way up.
You need 28, 3 by 3 convs
with that standard processing
stack before all of the 224
by 224 pixels in an image
you're looking at each other.
And what this means is
that in a ResNet 50,
the points on the very
edge of the pixels
actually never see each other.
And it's a little bit--
I found this a little
bit counterintuitive.
But it suggests that we
really are constraining
quite a lot, the functions
that are easy to express
with these models.
And so there are some
functions of images
you just can't capture
with a ResNet 50.
On the other hand, if you
look at an architecture that
has global attention
over the full input, so
the transformers, you
could scale it that way
or in a perceiver, we're
going to be talking about all
of the pixels can interact.
So the model can basically
capture these things
and express these
functions much more
easily than can be expressed in
things that put locality first.
The other sort of
interesting property
of these sorts of architectures
is that position is featurized.
And this basically
means that we're
no longer sort of encoding
the architectural location
of something to figure
out where it's located
with respect to the other ones.
And this allows the
network to basically use
any positional information
that it wants but can also
discard it as it prefers.
And so this is the
standard way it's
done, of course, in the
context of architectures
that use Fourier or
sinusoidal-like features.
But there's a lot
of flexibility here.
OK, so now just
thinking in terms
of how ConvNets relate
to transformers sort
of at the opposite
end, it may look
like that we have
sort of a scalability
versus generality trade off.
And so if we look at ConvNets
the way that they're applied,
so typically we can
think about using them
on grid structure data.
There are, of course,
generalizations of convolutions
that work on data sets with
more interesting topology.
But typically we
can think of them
as operating on grids
in some sort of space.
Whereas, transformers
apply to generic sets.
So transformers are more
general from this point of view.
On the other hand, they
scale much, much worse.
So ConvNets are linear both in
the input points, the filter
size, and the number of
layers of that architecture,
whereas transformers have
this quadratic scaling
and they're still
linear in the depth.
So from this point
of view, what we're
interested in doing in
the perceiver line of work
was to scale transformers but to
keep the generality properties.
So we want something that lives
in between these two extremes.
And the way that we
do this is by looking
at self-attention and sort
of modifying it in a way that
allows us to scale better.
So to walk through what
self-attention actually
does in sort of
standard transformers,
we take our input array, which
here is written as the number--
as the indices, which
is the number of tokens
or the number of
pixels, basically
the number of input units
depending what you're
looking at, and the channels.
We have a 1D convolution.
So this is O of M
with respect to the Q,
K, and V. We then compute
the attention maps using
the output of this operation.
This gives us a
matrix multiply, which
is the source of the
quadratic scaling.
And then finally, we
compute output features
with another matrix multiply.
We're already rate limited
here, because for even
standard resolution
images, M is quite large.
So it's around 50,000 for
standard ImageNet images,
which again are very small.
So this is something
that just isn't
going to work if we
want deep architectures.
So what we do is we replace, at
the input to the architecture
we replace the self-attention
with a cross-attention layer.
And we do this using
basically a learned query.
And so we're replacing only
the query from the input here
with a learned component.
And so these indices
and channels,
you can just think
of these as basically
working like the learned
initial state for an RNN.
there's a variety of
names that this idea
goes under in the literature.
We refer to them as latents.
But they're sometimes
called inducing
points or other things.
So the basic idea is we're
learning the input to the query
and keeping the key
value input the same.
The downside or the
sort of upside of this
is that when we compute the
attention map after this, now
we basically turned this
from a square matrix
to a rectangular matrix--
and reduces the complexity
of the matrix multiplied
to O of MN, so now it's
linear in the input size.
And the second matrix multiply
has the exact same property.
So it from quadratic,
it becomes linear.
And the quite cool
thing about this
is that, OK, so
the cross-attention
is linear in complexity, but
the output is actually smaller.
And so this, I
think, is actually
the more important point here.
It's that this allows us
to map something which
is quite large into something
that has size that's
independent of the input.
So we have full control over
this as a hyperparameter.
And this allows us to build deep
networks on top of this latent.
So because this is of a small
size that we can control,
we can afford to have quadratic
complexity on top of this.
And so we use this--
yep?
I'm sorry.
I'm still a little
bit confused as to how
you guys are able to turn
this square into a rectangle
in the second step.
Is it because you
replaced the query
with the learned something
that is significantly
smaller compared to the
input size in the first step?
Yeah, that's exactly right.
So if you look at the--
so the underlying
matrix multiply here,
which is written as
the QK transpose,
so the outer dimension
here has shape N, which
is determined by the query.
And so by shrinking
that query, we're
just changing the output
of the matrix multiply.
OK.
Thank you.
Yeah, so I guess--
sorry, go ahead please.
OK, cool.
So basically you only do
that for the query, right?
So key and value remain
the original size
matrices, correct?
That's right, yeah.
OK.
But so basically-- so I
don't know what I'm not
understanding basically.
So the problem for me is that
for a query, now in my head
I'm looking for let's
say, I have the ith token,
now there is no
ith query anymore.
Doesn't that cause a problem
when I'm trying to use it
and to compute scores?
Yeah.
So what's happening
here is you're
comparing-- you'll have a
smaller subset of query.
So if you think about this
and not in terms of the matrix
multiplies but in
terms of comparing
each query to each key, so
in normal self-attention
we have one query for
each key, so every point
compares to every other point.
Right?
So here what we've done
is instead of comparing
every point to
every other point,
we have a set of sort
of cluster centers--
you may be able to
think about them as.
So that's a smaller number.
And we compare each of those
to each of the input points.
But we don't know which
tokens technically belong
to which clusters, right?
That's right.
So it has to be learned.
Through Matmuls.
Yeah, exactly.
So one way to think about this,
about what's happening here
is that instead of-- so
in a normal self-attention
transformer, by comparing all
to all we're sort of saying,
OK, I know what the
feature is at this point
and I want it to attend
to similar features.
Here what we're saying
is we're learning
a bunch of supplementary
points that
should be sort of
maximally similar
to some subset of the inputs,.
So correct me if I'm wrong
but this is essentially
using a hard engine, right?
We're using a-- it's about
like declaring all the points.
It's like some points, which
we think are very similar,
and only were self-attention
was so hardened like this points
you're sharing, right?
Yeah.
So they're related.
That would be one way
to think about it.
The slight modifier
to that idea,
though, is that they basically
live in an abstract space.
So they're not
assigned sort of one
to one, to one of
the input queries
or to one of the input points.
They're sort of learned, so they
can be somewhere in the middle.
But I think that's a good
way to think about it,
that's a good intuition.
But I guess one of the places
where I'm a little confused
here is you have here indices
and indices for the twos,
likessssssssssss
sssssssssssssssssssssssssssssss
the purple and green
matrices of the far left.
But those indices
are not necessarily
corresponding to inputs.
Like in the NLP space,
those would not necessarily
be tokens, right?
These are just sort of--
Exactly.
But the matrix in this
case is the result
of some kind of mapping from
the input tokens to an N
by D matrix, is that right?
No, it's actually--
so it basically
acts like it's a
learned set of weights.
It's one way to think about it.
So they function exactly
the same way that
learned position encodings do.
So it's basically just
a learned embedding.
But it's not
conditioned on anything.
It's just sort of
a set of weights.
Oh, OK.
That makes more sense.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
OK, so if there are
no more questions,
I'm going to keep going.
But of course, feel
free to interrupt me.
So the way that given
this idea, so we have this
learned latent
array, which again it
functions sort of like an
RNN in an initial state
or it's a set of weights.
We basically randomly
initialize that.
And then we use this to attend
onto the input byte array.
And so the byte array here is
the flattened set of pixels
for example for ImageNet.
And the output of this is
going to live in the same space
as-- so the same index space
as the latent array does.
And there's residual
connections in the way
that you would normally do in
an attention layer as well.
So once we're in the space, we
can then build an architecture
by using a standard transformer
but phrased in the latent space
rather than in the input space.
And this is going to allow
us to basically end up,
because we sort of
distilled the input down
to the smaller space.
We can still flexibly allow all
of these points to interact.
So this should be still
as nearly as expressive
as a normal transformer is.
And then each of
the modules here now
is quadratic in the latent size
rather than the input size.
So this is something that
we can control quite a lot.
So in the original
version of the procedure,
we found it was very helpful to
have additional cross attends.
So this is certainly
something that you could do.
And the reason-- the
intuition behind this
is that this bottleneck
is quite severe.
We can't maintain all of the
information from the input,
and so we want
these queries, which
are now sort of
conditioned on the past
to be able to look back
at the input point.
And so this is something that we
found to be quite helpful when
tuning for the first paper.
But the caveat, I will say,
is that we're no longer
recommending this
as best practice,
because these cross attentions
end up being quite heavy.
But this is something that
you can explore certainly
if you want sort of more
conditional queries,
or if you want to be able to
cross attend to new inputs that
are coming in.
The other thing that
we found quite helpful
in the context of data sets that
have a limited amount of data,
which for these architectures
includes ImageNet,
is to allow weight
sharing in depth.
And so this basically
just amounts
to tying the weights
for the different cross
attention and different
self-attention layers
as they're repeated.
So this ends up looking like an
RNN that's unrolled in depth.
At a high level, this
gives us an architecture
that we can apply to images.
But it doesn't make
any assumptions
about image structure.
So it's one that you
can use elsewhere.
And we basically, we give
information about the input
sort of spatial structure by
having positional coatings
and here we use a 2D Fourier
feature position encoding.
And just to show you what that
looks like here to give you
a sense, so each of the
input points is assigned.
Basically, so you'll
be some position here.
And we have sinusoidal and
cosinusoidal features in 2D.
So this is basically a
Fourier decomposition
of the position of the 2D input.
And a couple of things that we
found with that, if we sampled
the frequency, that's the
maximum frequency that's
used up to the Nyquist
frequency of the signal,
we end up doing
better than if you
use a lower version of this.
And this basically
is because this
will allow every
other point to be
aware of every distinct
point in the image.
Whereas if you sample
at a lower frequency,
you're going to end
up with aliasing.
And so not all points
will be sort of legible.
We also found that sampling
the spectrum relatively densely
tends to help and
the contrast here
at the time we were developing
was with respect to NeRF.
So NeRF, at least in
earlier implementations,
used quite a small number
of frequency bands.
We found that the more we
added the better we did.
So in general, this is
something to be attentive to.
An then, finally, as opposed
to language where you typically
have addition of
whatever you're embedding
is with the sinusoidal or
position encoding that you use.
Here we found that
concatenating them
performed consistently better.
And so this may be
because the positioning,
the content embedding is not
as sparse as it is in language.
We're not totally sure.
But this is something that
I observed consistently.
And before I move on to results.
I just want to contrast this
to some other approaches
for using transformers
in the image context.
So the obvious precedent
here is visual transformers.
And I think this line of
work is great, especially
in the image context, but
there are some caveats about it
that make it less suitable for
sort of more general purpose
use.
So one is that-- so
vision transformers
do use an input 2D convolution.
So this is often
phrased in terms
of patches, input patches,
the special case of a 2D
transformer.
So it does restrict the class
of inputs you can use it for.
And because we're basically
building this patching
or convolution
into it, this means
that this has an approach
really isn't sufficient to get
it to work on non-grid data.
There are other ways
you could adapt it,
but this is something
that you will
have to special case for every
domain you're looking at.
And then finally, because we
have this input where we're
telling the architecture
what it should look at first
in the initial grouping,
this does amount
to getting rid of the
non-locality assumption.
It's not super clear doing
much doing this just once will
make a difference.
But this is something to be
aware of when you're thinking
about this architecture.
And then finally cross-attention
itself is used quite broadly
in the vision literature.
So to highlight a couple
of examples, DETR,
which is an object detection
method from Facebook,
basically, has a
convolutional backbone
that's then used to give
an output feature map.
This is then passed into a
transformer encoder-decoder.
And of course, whenever
you hear encoder-decoder,
you can cross-attention because
from the encoder to the decoder
there's a cross-attention step.
And so they're using
basically the cross-attention
to go from some feature
map representation
to something that looks more
like the object bounding boxes.
There's also quite
nice work on learning
self-supervised or unsupervised
object segmentation models.
And in this work, they're
doing something very similar,
where they have a
convolutional backbone.
They then use something like
these latent the latency
that we introduce here to do to
what they call them slots here.
But basically, to assign
some of the output
pixels to different slots,
so that they sort of
have independent complementary
decoding of the slots
in the segmentation model here.
And there's a lot
of other things, OK.
So now I'm going to walk you
through results of this model.
Hi, can I-- oh, go ahead.
I'll go after you.
Go for it.
OK, cool, sorry for that.
Can you go back a
couple of slides,
where you had how the inputs
flow into I think one--
yeah, that one.
OK, so I have two questions.
The latent transformer
is basically
like a self-attention.
Is that correct?
Yeah, so the latent
transformer is a fully
self-attentional transformer.
Got it.
Why-- see, for
the key and value,
they flow directly into
your cross-attention.
And there is the query
also flowing into it.
But the latent array is flowing
into the cross-attention
in parallel to the query.
Can you explain that?
Yeah, so this is just--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Yeah, it's meant to depict
the residual connection.
So the cross-attention--
this is sort
of a cross-attention depicted
as a cross-attention module.
And so the cross-attention
itself has the attention,
it has a residual connection,
and then there's an MLP.
So that's what that's
meant to indicate.
OK.
But it's basically--
the QKV is standard.
Got it.
Thanks.
Hi, I had a question that
is slightly related to this.
So you can just stay on
this slide, actually.
So I think one thing that's
interesting about this--
I lost you.
You're cutting off.
It's mostly consisting
of attention layers,
whether it's attention
or image transformers.
Can you hear me?
Is that coming through?
No, it's cutting off.
I think--
But I think some--
Oh, OK.
Should I type it?
Is that-- should I type it?
Yeah, that's a good idea.
I'll type it.
Thanks, sorry.
No worries.
Feel free to go ahead.
I'll type it slowly.
Sounds good.
Sounds good to me.
Actually, can I chime in?
Drew, while you're on that
previous slide on the flow,
so these residual
connections, I actually
didn't know that
cross-attention used them.
How reliant are these sequential
cross-attention layers
on the residual connections?
Yeah, so here, in the initial--
so the two things
I will say is that
in the initial cross-attention,
it doesn't really
make a difference, if it's
something we've ablated.
When we get to the Perceiver
IO version of this,
we also did the same thing in
the decoder cross-attention.
And it can make some of--
it can make a difference there,
depending on what you're doing.
I think it's actually
essential in the content--
when you're using repeated
cross-attention this way,
so when you have this sort
of iterative structure.
And the reason for
this is that the thing
that's actually used
to condition the query
is basically all--
that's your full representation
of this sort of the state
of the architecture so far.
And so the skip
connection is from--
it's in, basically
the query channel.
It's in the latent space.
And so this is
basically what allows
you to end up with this sort of
dense and stable architecture.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
So to ImageNet.
OK, so in standard
ImageNet processing,
basically, we compare
against a few--
so this is a little bit
out of date at this point,
but against a few just sort of
sanity check baselines here.
So comparing against ResNet50,
and then at the time,
the best vision
transformer model
that was purely on ImageNet.
And we're definitely
in the ballpark.
This isn't-- these aren't
anywhere near state of the art
results.
But this is an architecture
that, again, it's
not using any 2D convolutions.
And so the fact that it was
able to do this well was,
we found, very, very
surprising at the time.
One of the quite cool
things about this
is that because this
architecture is not
making any assumptions,
the architecture itself
isn't making any assumptions
about the spatial structure
of the input images.
We can look at
permuted ImageNet.
And in the first version of
this, what we do is basically
we compute the features
using the 2D position.
So the 2D position is sort
of fixed to a position--
to the pixel.
And then we just shuffle it all.
And so this is
basically-- will give you
a sense of how dependent
the baselines are
on the input image structure.
And so if we look at the
transformer perceiver,
by construction,
they don't change.
So this is not an
empirical finding.
This is a property
of the models.
But we find that
ResNet50 falls by--
the performance
falls by about half.
And ViT, which again,
only has one layer where
it's relying on the
spatial structure also
has about a 15 point drop.
And so this suggests
that it's relying
quite a lot on
that very first one
to give it some information
about the structure.
We can push this
a little bit by,
instead of relying on
2D Fourier features,
learning completely learned
positional encodings.
And this basically-- this
is an architecture now--
this is a model that has
absolutely no information
about the input structure.
And so shuffling them
and learning them again
is absolutely equivalent.
And we find that this
architecture also
can be pushed above 70%.
And we've gotten slightly
better numbers here.
In general, this
seems to work worse.
So the 2D information is useful.
But it's quite cool
that you can get
what would have been
numbers comparable to state
of the art about five
or six years ago.
So this is quite cool.
Sorry, I'm a little thick here.
You're saying the difference
between the last two rows
is that the second-to-last row
has a two-dimensional position
embedding, and the last one
has a one-dimensional position
embedding, essentially,
is that right?
So it's learned.
So it's basically.
It'll be-- it's a, I believe,
a 256 dimensional vector
that's learned.
But it doesn't-- it basically--
it means that the
model itself has
no information about the
input spatial structure.
So the 2D positional
encodings that we're
using end up having about 200--
it's 200 some
features, depending
on what you're looking at.
But they're always-- they give
you very detailed information
about the 2D structure
of the input,
because they're based on
a Fourier decomposition
of the input space.
OK, that makes sense.
Thank you.
Hi, Drew.
Can I ask a question
about frequency
that you used to generate those
[INAUDIBLE] a couple of slides
before.
Yeah, this slide.
So basically, I have taken some
lectures in signal processing.
And I know if I want
to avoid aliasing,
I need to sample with at
least Nyquist frequency.
So I'm curious to know why do
you use frequencies starting
from one to the
Nyquist frequency
instead of starting
from Nyquist frequency
to some very high frequency?
I see, so basically, so the
maximum frequency that's used
is always Nyquist.
So anything above Nyquist
is going to be aliased.
So you're not actually going
to be able to resolve it.
Because it's in
pixel space, right?
So we sample--
1 is basically just
giving you an oscillation
that covers the entire image.
And so this is basically just
to sample of the full range
of non-aliased frequencies.
Oh, OK, cool, thank you, got it.
OK, so after the
ImageNet results,
we wanted to try it
on other domains.
And in particular, we
were interested in how
this could be used to work on
sort of multimodal domains,
so ones combining
various different types
of input features.
And one challenge or
one sort of problem
that you encounter in
these sorts of spaces
is that the data from
different modalities
end up having
different features.
And they always have
different semantics.
So if you take the
positional encoding
plus the RGB for
video, you end up
with some number of channels.
And then if you have
audio, that corresponds--
the data may be paired, but it
tends to have fewer features.
And it only has a 1D
positional encoding.
So the way that we
handle this is basically
by learning modality
specific position encodings.
And so these are
basically embeddings
that are special and learned
for each of the modalities.
And what this does is
basically tags-- ends up
tagging the features that
come from audio or video
with some information
that the network can
learn that allows it to
distinguish which one's which.
But given these padded, these
sort of learned, padded feature
vectors, we then
concatenate them all.
And that's how we
process multimodal data.
So basically, the input
to the architecture
still looks like
just one big array.
It's just that when
constructing this,
we know that some
of those features,
some of the rows in that
array, come from video
and some come from audio.
But the model itself isn't
given information about that,
other than what it learns.
We also have some questions.
[INAUDIBLE] can go first.
You're muted.
Yeah, sorry.
I thought I was muted now.
Yeah, sure.
If you can you hear me,
this is a super easy one.
I haven't been studying a lot
transformer stuff normally,
so I just didn't know what
positional embedding was.
Oh, so what is
positional embedding?
Yes, so basically a
positional embedding is--
it's a feature that says this--
so the simplest way to
think about it is in text.
So text, the input is 1D.
So things live in
some 1D sequence.
And for each point there,
you featurize where
it's located in that sequence.
So the simplest
thing to do would
be if you have negative
1 to 1 is the full range,
it just denotes actually where
it's located in that sequence.
But we typically
will add sort of--
we'll want to
featurize allows this
to have more dimensions
than just a single one.
And so the Fourier transpose--
the Fourier decomposition
is one way to do this
to sort of give it
privileged information about
the high frequency structure.
But we can also just use
the position to index
on to some embedding array,
which is how we do it
when we're learning things.
So basically, it's
just a set of weights
that are added to the
feature for that point that
give the network information
about where it's located
in the ground truth sequence.
OK, you want to go next?
Sorry, I had to find a
mute button, unmute button.
OK, so I actually
have two questions
regarding to the
Fourier features.
The I think, do you guys sample
them uniformly or are they--
do you like to learn these?
Yeah, so basically, we
sample them linearly.
So basically, we
take the full space
and we sample them linearly
with whatever the budget is.
There are-- so in
various settings,
we have actually
tried learning these.
So you could actually
initialize an array with them
and then learn them.
And that does help
sometimes, actually.
And you could
potentially learn--
you could try a more
sophisticated strategy on this,
too.
OK, cool.
My follow-up question
is that basically, I
feel like the selling
point of your research,
right, is that you don't make
any structural assumptions,
right?
You can take any type of format.
However, for the encoding,
wouldn't the dimensionality,
so for example, if
it's text, it's 1D,
right, if it's an image, it will
be 2D, and if it's like a video
it would be 3D.
You have more-- the positional
encoding will have more points,
right?
Wouldn't that inherently give
away the nature of the input?
Yeah, so it does.
So I completely agree with this.
You're totally right.
The version of this where we
have learned position encodings
is the most pure from
that point of view.
So it's one that gives it
basically no information
about the ground truth
spatial structure.
What it does give
the model, so when
you do the learned
position encoding,
it will say that,
for example, there
is a correspondence between
point k on image one
and point k on image two.
So that's basically the
least amount of information
you can give it
while still allowing
it to sort of figure out what
the structural relationship
between the input points is.
So this is the direction that
we've been trying to push in.
In general, giving the
architecture access
to sort of ground truth
structural information
like this lives on this
point in 2D is helpful.
So there's a couple
of things here.
There's sort of from a
practical point of view,
if you want good results, you
need to exploit these things.
Or it's helpful to
exploit these things.
But we do want to
move in the direction
where we're relying
on these things less.
And so this is
basically something
we're actively looking into.
OK, makes sense.
Thank you.
So I think [AUDIO OUT]
has posted her question
on the chat.
I also see you have
your hand raised.
So if you want, you
can give it a try.
If not, I'll read
out the question.
OK, I'll try.
Just let me know if it's choppy.
Yeah, so is it good right now?
So far so good.
Oh good, OK cool.
So I'm just curious, looking
at the perceiver diagram
you had, it's a bunch
of attention layers,
the cross-attention
and self-attention.
And I think there's
been this small trend
in recent work in
vision transformers
to try to sort of replace
the last few layers instead
of having attention,
like make them
be convolutions to address
this attention scaling problem,
right, in a different manner.
And so here, the
perceiver architecture
is trying to make
self-attention less expensive.
And there, they're just
trying to replace it.
And they kind of just
avoid the problem.
And so I'm curious--
and so I've seen
papers both ways,
some that try to do
things like the ones
you cited, and then some they're
trying to do this as well.
And in my mind, everyone always
has the good results and stuff.
So I'm curious if you
think there's a reason
to do one or the
other, or if you
think this alternative
approach is also promising,
or is there reason
research should go
in one direction or the other?
Yeah, so to my mind,
the big trade-off
is one between-- so the
vision literature, I think,
it's just exploded in terms
of these sort of hybrids.
And people trying to find
the right-- the exact right
place on the Pareto
curve for the trade-off
of speed and performance.
But they're basically
looking primarily
on vision specific problems.
So something-- the
computer vision community
itself typically doesn't
regularize itself away
from things that don't work
on things that aren't vision.
So you end up with things
that are very, very efficient
and very performant
on vision problems.
And so I think from
that point of view,
it's an incredibly
important line of work.
And that's probably the
right way of doing things.
But what we're sort of
aiming for is something--
is the things that are as
general as possible while still
kind of being performant.
Got it.
So this kind of
thing is critical--
Oh sorry to cut you off.
Go ahead.
No, no, please go ahead.
I was going to say-- so
this kind of thing is--
it's important.
Just to summarize,
so you feel like it's
important to focus on
attention, because that's
kind of critical for NLP.
You can't just sort put in
a convolution at the end
and sort of fix the problem.
But in vision maybe
you can, and it's fine.
Is that a right way
of understanding it?
That's part of it.
Vision and NLP aren't
the only two domains.
And so the thing that
we're really basically-- so
the kinds of problems that we're
interested in doing with this
include things like event-based
cameras, cell biology,
sort of proteins, all of
these sorts of things,
where we may or may not have the
right convolutional inductive
biases to even know how to
build those sorts of things.
They end up being whole
research programs,
like the mesh-based
convolution work.
Oh, cool, thank you.
I also have one more question
about the architecture.
So I saw that-- and I'm
sorry if you said this
and I just missed it.
But you had cross-attention and
then the latent transformer,
and then cross-attention.
I'm curious what
happens if you replace
the self-attention in those
layers with cross attention.
Does it affect your accuracy?
Is that even feasible?
Is that a valid question?
Yeah, so the sort of
thing that you could do
is you could modify this to
make it sort of hierarchical.
So that there are multiple
stages of cross-attention.
We haven't gotten
this working yet.
But it doesn't mean
it's not a good idea.
So there might be-- there
might be a right way
to do this that we haven't
figured out, right?
But it's something we
have tried a little bit.
Oh, cool, OK, thank you so much.
I appreciate it.
Yeah, no problem.
OK, let me--
I think we're running
short on time.
So maybe I'll skip ahead.
So before we run out
of too much time,
I want to at least talk
about the modifications
to this architecture that
we've made to make it work
sort of even more generally.
So one of the problems with
sort of the first architecture
that we looked at here,
the basic procedure,
is that it works basically
for arbitrary inputs.
But it's designed to work
only on classification
and regression
tasks as an output.
And so basically,
we wanted to see
if we could use the same
cross-attention strategy
for decoding.
And it turns out, you can.
It's something that works
pretty well just kind of out
of the box.
So the idea is that
we have-- if we
have our cross-attention
input and self-attention
sort of to do the
processing, we can introduce
a set of additional queries.
And these are
basically queries that
give the semantics
of each of the points
that you're trying to decode.
And we pass these as input to
another cross-attention layer,
which is configured in
basically the opposite way
that the encoder
cross-attention is configured.
So now, the queries are
going to be something
that's potentially large.
And the keys and values are
coming from this latent.
And so what this allows
us to do basically
is to keep all of
the nice advantages
of the original perceiver.
So we have an encoder
that scales linearly.
We have a processor stage, this
sort of latent self-attention
that scales independently
of the input size.
And we now have a decoder
that keeps the decoupling,
but gives us linear scaling
with respect to output size.
And so by doing this, we
can now basically apply
the same approach to
basically dense output tasks.
And so to give you a sense
of how this works, just
sort of intuitively, if
we're doing autoencoding
on this image of
puppies, basically what
we do is we encode,
process, and then to decode,
we take a query that corresponds
to each of the points.
And then we pass it
into this decoder.
So we can query
one of the points,
we get one pixel, query another
one, we get another one.
And all the way up, until
we get all 10,000 points.
And that's how we can do
reconstruction with this.
And the cool thing about
this is that it opens up
a bunch of new applications.
And we can get different
kinds of outputs
just by changing how
the queries work.
So if we want to do something
like multimodal autoencoding,
where we have some of
the outputs or videos,
we use the same construction
trick to get positions that--
to get queries that have
the relevant semantics
for each of the points
that we're decoding.
And we can do this,
even though, basically,
the sizes of these
different data,
so the number of points
they have is quite diverse.
So in the multimodal
autoencoding experiments
that we have in this paper,
we do this for video, audio,
and labels at the same time.
So that all of them
are just passed
into their uniform network
and then decoded one
by one in this way.
But we can also do masked
language modeling now
by conditioning on the
position in a sequence.
We can do multitask
classification
by having basically an index
that gives which task you're
querying from the network.
And we can do things
like optical flow
by passing in input features
as well as the positions.
And so I'm just going
to just quickly skip
to a couple of the different--
I can share these slides with
you, with you all afterwards,
to look through them.
Some of these things
are quite cool.
But just quickly, I want
to talk about language
and then optical flow.
So for language,
basically, what we
wanted to do with this
was to see if we could use
this to replace tokenization.
And why might we care about
getting rid of tokenization?
So we use tokenization primarily
because transformers scale
poorly with sequence length.
And tokenizing cuts sequence
length by about a factor of 4.
But there are various
problems that arise with this.
And so why might we care
about removing tokenizers?
So for one, tokenizers perform
less well on rare words.
So if you compare the sort of
the byte based decomposition,
the UTF based--
UTF-8 encoding of an input--
of an input sequence like this,
you can see that
there's basically
a uniform allocation
of points in memory
to each of the input characters.
The exception are
diacritics, which
end up splitting it into two.
But if you look at the
SentencePiece tokenization,
so it's learned that
pepper is one token.
But jalapeno gets split
into five in this case.
So this basically says it's--
the amount of capacity
that you allocate
depends on how rare
the word is, which can
lead to suboptimal encodings.
They're also brittle to
subtle perturbations.
A famous example of this
is that if you enter--
so if you've ever played
around with GPT-3,
you'll notice that
the output can
be quite sensitive
if you add a space
or omit a space at the end.
And this basically
is because the space
can end up being factorized
into different parts
of the tokenization.
There are other
problems-- there are
other things that can
happen there, too,
but this is one cause of that.
And finally, tokens don't
transfer across languages.
So if you wanted to have a
model that, without any tuning,
could be used on many different
languages at the same time,
tokenizers are a
blocker for this.
So if we can get rid of them,
it'll simplify the pipeline.
It'll also make
things less brittle
and then hopefully lead
to more general models.
So the way that we do
masked language modeling
is the same as the
way that I showed
in that schematic
autoencoding experiment.
So we mask some fraction
of our inputs, about 15%
is sort of the
standard magic number.
We then decode at each of the
positions that are masked.
And we task the model with
decoding whatever characters
were masked at those locations.
And then once we
have this model,
so this is what we
do for pre-training,
we can then fine tune it
by replacing the decoder
with a multitask decoder
that takes in the tasks
that we're using on the
downstream evaluation
setting and training the model
to reconstruct the logits
on a per task basis.
OK, so to look at how
this model performs,
we basically first
compare it to BERT Base.
So this is just
a solid benchmark
that we understand very well.
And first, by looking
at sort of matched
two models that
have matched FLOPs,
we can see that Perceiver IO
and BERT Base work on par.
You see there's a
different trade-off here.
So to get the same
number of FLOPs,
basically, we make
Perceiver IO deeper.
And this ends up giving
it more parameters.
But on a per FLOPs
basis, it ends up
performing about the same.
On the other hand, if we
remove the tokenizer from BERT
and keep the FLOPs
the same, we see
that the number of
parameters-- the number
of parameters and the depth
just drastically fall down.
And this is because
BERT scales quite poorly
with sequence length, because
it uses a normal transformer.
But if we use a perceiver
without the tokenization,
we can see that we only
get a slight reduction
in the number of parameters
at the FLOPs count.
But the performance performs
almost exactly the same.
So this means that the
perceiver in this setting
is performing basically
the same with and without
the tokenization.
It's learning a
different strategy.
It's using different parameters.
But it basically can be brought
to the same performance.
We can then scale
this more by sort
of leaning into what happens
in the tokenizer free setting.
And we see that we can
get a moderate performance
boost as well.
I think it's also-- in
the language setting,
it's also useful to look
at what the attention--
the attention maps that
are sort of learned.
And what's being visualized
here are basically,
for each of the latents, for
some subset of the latents,
we're looking at where
it's attending to
in the input sequence.
And some of these
end up being local,
so looking at specific
points in the sentence.
Some of them are
periodic, so they
look sort of at recurring
points over the sequence.
And some of them also
look like they pick out
syntactic features,
which is quite nice.
So they pick out,
basically, exclamation
points, or capital letters,
or other punctuation that's
quite useful and
decodable from right
at the beginning
of the sequence.
We can also basically use
this exact same architecture
on optical flow.
And optical flow is basically
an important classical problem
in computer vision, where given
a pair of frames in a video,
we want to basically
track all of the points,
so figure out the motion from
every point from one frame
to the other.
And so optical flow
is usually visualized
using this sort of
colorized images
that are shown in the bottom.
And what this
gives you basically
is a per pixel indication of the
velocity at every single point.
And so you can see that--
so the blade the
character here is holding
is moving to the right.
Whereas, this
creature behind her
is sort of moving
as moving downwards.
So there are a couple of
problems with optical flow
that make it interesting
to sort of approach.
So one, it's a dense task.
And it basically involves
long range correspondences.
But the standard training
protocol, there's
basically no large scale
realistic training data,
just because it's
incredibly hard
to sort of label all of the
pixels in a real world scene
and figure out where they go to.
So the typical way to do this is
to train on some synthetic data
and then evaluate on
more realistic scenes.
And optical flow is
also interesting,
because it's basically
the locus of some
of the most complicated
visual architectures
in the literature.
So the previous state-of-the-art
result here is this method
called RAFT, which won the best
paper award at ECCV last year.
And I'm just highlighting
this to give you
a sense of how much work
people do into sort of hand
engineering these architectures.
So this is a very, very
cleverly designed architecture.
And basically it incorporates
things like global correlation
volumes that are explicitly
computed at different offsets
to basically allow the
model to reason about how
things at different
scales are moving
with respect to each other.
It also has local neighborhood
gather operations, as well as
update blocks to
keep track of what's
happening within each
specific correlation block.
And then finally, there's
a flow specific upsampling
operators that were developed.
So in contrast to
this, we're basically--
we wanted to see how well
Perceiver IO would do here.
And just to give
you a sense of sort
of what we were expecting
coming into this,
we thought, well, maybe--
so Perceiver IO is throwing
a lot of the structure away.
So we were hoping that we
would get some good results.
But it would probably overfit.
And there's this sort of
problem of the domain transfer
that's happening here.
But on the other
hand, self-attention
seems to be a reasonable
way to match this sort
of correspondence thing.
What we actually found was
that just by doing the very,
very simple preprocessing here,
so extracting basically a patch
around each pixel and then
using the standard Perceiver IO
architecture, we were able to
get state-of-the-art results
here.
And so this is
basically was validation
of this general
approach of trying
to have general purpose
architectures that
would transfer over.
And so basically
with minimal tuning,
we are able to get
results that are
both of the sort of
compelling benchmarks
on both of the Sintel, the
Sintel evaluation methods,
and to get comparable
results on KITTI.
So these are the standard ones.
And we can also
sort of visualize
what happens when we apply
this on real world data.
So there's no ground truth here.
So you-- we can't
really compare it.
But it's still useful to sort
of see how it moves around.
And we can see that
qualitatively, it's
able to capture a lot
of the fine structure
and to sort of get the right
motion for the things that
are very clearly moving
in the specific direction.
We can also sort of--
it's also, I think,
informative to look
at what happens--
how it managed to--
how it manages to represent
sort of small structure.
Is this video playing?
Yeah, we can see it.
OK, cool.
So the thing to look at here
is the fine water droplets
that are sort of flying through
the air as that bird flies by.
And because we're decoding
at every single output point,
the architecture is
able to represent those.
So it's able to capture very,
very fine scale segmentation
that would be
difficult to capture
if you had, for example, a
convolutional upsampler here.
OK, so I'm just going
to-- also, the light
might've just gone
off in this room.
I'm just going to--
Also try a task
like gap estimation,
because Perceiver IO looks
like it can also work
very well on that modalities.
Yeah, so we haven't
published anything.
But some internal
results suggest
that it works just fine.
There basically--
there don't seem
to be-- one of the
surprising things, the things
that we were a little
bit unsure about was
how much information was going
to be contained in this latent.
Because basically, you're
abstracting quite a lot.
And you're not-- it doesn't have
any 2D structure intrinsically.
But it does seem
like that it seems
to be able to represent
things quite well.
And these sorts of
decoding mechanisms
do seem to be able to do that.
Got it, OK.
So I'm just going to--
in the interest of time,
I'm going to skip ahead
to the conclusion.
Drew, I had one
question with respect
to the metrics that you've
shared for the optical flow,
the number.
So in the table, it was like
Sinel.final, clean, and KITTI
were these different data
sets or different metrics,
same metric for
different sets or these
are three different metrics?
Yeah, so these are three
different data sets.
So Sintel.clean and
Sintel.final are basically two--
they're two ways of doing the
final rendering for Sintel.
In all cases, these
methods are trained just
on the autoflow data set.
So they're trained on this
sort of general purpose
kind of wacky synthetic
motion data set.
And then we're
evaluation-- we're
evaluating on these different
domains without fine tuning.
OK.
Yeah, the flow has quite--
the data sets are quite small.
So it's generally even
problematic to fine tune.
Thank you.
OK, so just to summarize--
What is the ground truth
to find the point error?
Yeah, so the way
this works is Sintel
is a computer-- it's basically
a relatively high quality CGI
movie that was
basically open-source.
And so they actually
have the ground truth.
So if you know the ground
truth and the state,
you can compute the pixel
correspondence from frame
to frame.
So that's what's used on Sintel.
And then KITTI, they
basically have--
they have a LIDAR sensor
that's used to figure out
the depth of all points.
And then they compute
the correspondences.
So the ground truth is actually
the ground truth optical flow.
But in general, it's hard
to get dense optical flow.
It's very expensive
to collect it.
Great, thanks.
OK, so the-- so basically,
just to summarize,
so the perceivers are
attention-based architectures
that scale linearly and
work as drop-in replacements
for transformers on a
variety of settings.
They also seem to be able
to achieve results that
are comparable, at
least, in performance
with models that rely
on 2D convolutions.
But of course, there
is a trade-off here.
And so it's good to
be very aware of this,
of generality versus
speed in specific domains.
And so as was pointed
out in settings
where you can use
2D convolutions.
It's certainly good to
have them in the loop.
It's basically a
unified architecture
that allows joint modeling
of different modalities
of different sizes.
And basically, overall, it
seems to be a quite flexible
architecture that's able to
produce a state-of-the-art
or near state-of-the-art results
on a variety of different
domains.
And there's-- in the two papers,
we look at a number of other
domains that I
didn't talk about,
including 3D point
cloud modeling,
replacing the transformer
that's used in the StarCraft,
in the sort of StarCraft
behavioral cloning agent
and a couple of others.
So this does-- we
have a lot of evidence
that this general approach
seems to work broadly.
And there's a lot of things
we still haven't tried.
So we're very interested
in pushing this and always,
always open for
suggestions and so forth.
So we're relying on a
large body of related work,
because we're sort of drawing
from a lot of different areas
here.
So here are some highlights.
And then I just want to thank
my coauthors on this work.
And of course, I'm
happy to talk more.
Thanks, Drew.
Thanks a lot.
So one question I had
is so what do you think
is the future of similar models.
Do you think these
are going to be
used more in the sort
of transformer community
to replace ConvNet
and other stuff?
Yeah, so the-- I think, broadly
speaking, I think it's--
I think of perceivers
now as sort of--
because we know how to
adapt them pretty well
to sort of domains
where we don't have
a great idea of the right way
to structure an architecture,
an inductive bias.
So I think that's one of the
really strong cases for it,
so settings in which
you don't really
know what the right way
to structure a problem is.
I also think these
kinds of approaches
can be used in
conjunction with ConvNets
for sort of things that are
as domain agnostic as needed.
But I think multimodal and
new domains is really--
that's where these
are obvious choices.
Also, what do you think are the
current bottlenecks with this?
And if you don't mind,
if you can disclose,
what are you working on
towards next with this stuff?
So I can't-- I can't talk about
too many details about that.
But a couple of domains--
so one, we don't really
have a great handle
on how to use them on
sort of small scale data,
so data where you don't have
the data to sort of recover
the inductive bias.
So this is, I think, a
really important area.
The other thing that we haven't
sort of talked about here,
but you could probably imagine
that we'd be thinking about
would be how to train on
multiple modalities or sort
of multiple things
at the same time.
So right now, all of
these architectures
are sort of trained
in isolation.
But there are a lot
of opportunities
for sort of figuring out how to
pose problems together and use
a single architecture
on all of them.
Got it.
Also, I'm sure if you've
tried, but can you also
use this for tabular data?
Yeah, so effectively,
the architecture
treats any input
data as tabular data.
So I think that's exactly the
right way to think about it.
Sounds good.
Thanks for the talk.
I will open mic general
questions for the students.
So stop the recording.